A Guide to the Bernardin-Dos Passos Research Collection
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Bernardin-Dos Passos Research Collection
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
12407
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The collection was given to the University of Virginia Library by Paul Bernardin on August 28, 2002
Scope and Content
The collection consists of the papers of Charles W. Bernardin during the years 1943 to 1974 while he was working on a manuscript about the life of John Dos Passos. The papers consist of 1100 items, 2 hollinger boxes and 4 boxes of notecards, making it 2 linear feet. Included in the collection is Chapter Thirteen, "A Place to Work," from his manuscript. There is also correspondence with Bernardin and people that knew Dos Passos in order to obtain facts about his life. Correspondents include Esther Andrews, Carlos Baker, William Rose Benet, Malcolm Cowley, Marion Cummings, S. Foster Damon, Lloyd and Marion Lowndes, Arthur K. McComb, Stewart Mitchell, Arthur Mizener, Joseph Moskowitz, Kenneth B. Murdock, Gerald Murphy, William Page, Dudley Poore, Martha Saxton, Gilbert Seldes, Paul Sifton, Mr. and Mrs. St. George, and Edmund Wilson. Other correspondents included potential publishers for the manuscript including the University of Oklahoma which had agreed to publish it. There are also book reviews, newspaper clippings, interviews of Dos Passos by Carlos Baker regarding meetings with Ernest Hemingway, notes on translations, an account of Spences Point, and several boxes of notecards with research notes. There are also letters between Bernardin, Dos Passos, and his attorney regarding tax deductions for Dos Passos after the writer gave his collection to the University of Virginia.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged alphabetically by topic. The correspondence is also alphabetical by last name of correspondent.
Contents List
- n. d. Manuscript Bernardin's unpublished writings on Dos Passos, 1 item (Box-folder 1:1)
  Chapter 13 "A Place to Work"
- 1965 Correspondence Charles Bernardin with Dos Passos, 3 items (Box-folder 1:2)
  Dos Passos asked Bernardin to provide biographical information to his lawyer, showing that Dos Passos was a major author of the twentieth century and could declare a tax deduction after giving his manuscripts and papers to the University of Virginia Special Collections Library
- 1948–1974 Correspondence of Bernardin with people who knew Dos Passos: A-L, 40 items (Box-folder 1:3)
  Correspondents include Esther Andrews, Carlos Baker, William Rose Benet, Malcohn Cowley, Marion Cummings, S. Foster Damon, Elizabeth and John Dos Passos, John Farrar, Franz J. Horch,W. Horsley Gantt, Robert Hillyer, Robert Latham, and Lloyd and Marion Lowndes.
- 1948–1974 Correspondence of Bernardin with people that knew Dos Passos M-W, 46 items (Box-folder 1:4)
  Correspondents include Arthur K. McComb, Stewart Mitchell, Arthur Mizener, Joseph Moskowitz, Kenneth B. Murdock, Gerald Murphy, William Page, Dudley Poore, Martha Saxton Gilbert Seldes, Paul Sifton, Mr. and Mrs. St. George, and Edmund Wilson
- 1943–1966 Correspondence of Bernardin about his manuscript on Dos Passos, 84 items (Box-folder 1:5)
  There are reference letters to libraries, institutions, and scholars in order to obtain information for his manuscript
- 1962–1963 Correspondence Dos Passos in Provincetown, 10 letters and 65 notecards (Box-folder 1:6)
- 1923–1930 Correspondence Dos Passos to Eugene Saxton and John Farrar, 19 letters and 70 notecards (Box-folder 1:7)
  There are photocopies of the letters. Summaries of letters are on the notecards
- 1950; n. d. Correspondence and research notes about translations of Dos Passos works, 17 items and 20 notecards (Box-folder 2:1)
- 1926; 1962; 1968 Dos Passos Interviews, 2 items and 15 notecards (Box-folder 2:2)
  Carlos Baker's notes on his interview with Dos Passos about his ten meetings with Ernest Hemingway in Paris, Key West, New York, and Havanna between 1917 and 1948. There is also an interview with Dos Passos by [David] Sanders from [Berkeley, California].
- n. d. List of illustrations, 6 items (Box-folder 2:3)
- n. d. Newspaper clippings and book reviews, 50 items (Box-folder 2:4)
- n. d. Newspaper clippings and book reviews, 50 items (Box-folder 2:5)
- 1963 Notes on Spences Point, 2 items (Box-folder 2:6)
- n. d. Quotations [for the manuscript], 25 items (Box-folder 2:7)
  There are pages of quotations that didn't have copyright issues
- 1938; 1950; n. d. Research notes on Dos Passos, 9 items (Box-folder 2:8)
- Index note cards with research notes, 200 items (Box 3)
- Index note cards with research notes, 100 items (Box 4)
- Index note cards with research notes, 200 items (Box 5)
- Index note cards with research notes, 100 items (Box 6)